Guide to Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, by Tatiana Warsher RL.11394
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Codex Topographicus Pompeianus
1937-1957 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Warsher, Tatiana
RL.11394
40 Volumes
40 volumes of Tatiana Warsher's bound manuscript, Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, detailing the archaeology and architecture of Pompeii, Italy. Volumes include typescripts, maps, photographs, and foldout pages describing streets, buildings, and art in and collected from Pompeii. This set of volumes was assembled by Michael Rostovtzeff, Warsher's mentor and a fellow scholar on Roman antiquities.
Biographical / Historical
Tatiana Warsher (1880-1960) was born in Moscow and attended the Women's College of the University of St. Petersburg from 1898-1901, where she studied with Michael Rostovtzeff. She first went to Pompeii in 1911, while on her honeymoon. Later widowed, she left Russia in 1921 and studied with Pompeian scholars Franz Noack and Gerhart Rodenwalt at the University of Berlin. In 1923 she reconnected with Rostovtzeff, who encouraged her to study Pompeii. She settled in Rome and joined the German Archaeological Institute, and began intensely studying Pompeii, taking frequent research trips to the site.
Warsher's first book was Pompeii in Three Hours, a guide book originally published in German in 1925, and later reissued in other languages. She then began compiling and writing the Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, manuscript volumes intended to document every detail about various areas within Pompeii, including photographs of the ruins, floorplans and drawings of the sites, and artwork preserved in various Pompeiian collections around Italy. Initially writing for the German Archaeological Institute's library, Warsher later made copies of the Codex that included additional information she had discovered since writing her initial volumes. Copies were distributed to the German Archaeological Institute, the American Academy in Rome, the Swedish Institute in Rome, and to Rostovtzeff's personal library, which was later given to the Duke University Classics Department (the volumes in this collection).
Warsher lived in Rome through World War II, and following the war re-established contact with American scholars. Her Codex volumes were microfilmed and distributed to libraries around the world.
Biography abridged from "Tatiana Warsher 1880-1960," by Lawrence Richardson, Jr.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Codex Topographicus Pompeianus was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from the Duke University Classics Dept. in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Codex Topographicus Pompeianus consists of manuscript volumes written by Tatiana Warsher between 1937 and 1957. Her mission and motivation in writing the Codex is explained in an undated preface in Volume 3 (focusing on Regio I, Insula 3):
"The work that I am now undertaking, the first completed section of which I offer in the following pages, is to be a descriptive album of photographs of all Pompeii thus far excavated, taken systematically, Insula by Insula. The illustrations are to be accompanied by a running description which will state briefly the essential features of each building in the Insula and of almost each particular illustrated. The need for such a complete and thorough work is great. It is superfluous for me to remark that Pompeii offers an inexhaustible source of first hand material for our study of the ancient world. Every archaeologist knows that in the ruins of Pompeii are hundreds of subjects for research, until now hardly touched upon, which when treated will contribute vastly to our knowledge of ancient Roman life. My album - Codex topographicus - will place this tremendous store house of material within easy reach."
In Volume 36 (focusing on Regio IX, Insula 3), Warsher's preface sheds light on her modest views of her research and its value for future scholarship:
"This is only a rough draft of a book that someone else must write, as Lawrence Richardson has now done with the house of Dioscuri. I have always considered my work that of laying foundations upon which others may build. I have repeatedly urged young students to concentrate their efforts on a single house in the hope that by doing so we shall preserve the fast-vanishing evidence of the excavations. No house merits such a study more than the Casa di Marco Lucrezio. Its difficult plan, its rich paintings, its epigraphical problems, its history are all fascinating. The[sic] let someone take what I offer here as a basis for farther study, elaborate and finish it."
Scholar Lawrence Richardson's biography of Warsher explains that her Codex underwent multiple revisions as she created and distributed new copies of each volume for her mentor, Michael Rostovtzeff, as well as for other scholars and libraries. The volumes in this collection represent the most complete set available in a single research library.
Each volume describes a specific region and zone within Pompeii, indicated by the volume's title. Warsher's photography, cartography, and research about each area's geography, architecture, archaeology, and artwork is included alongside pages of her typescript descriptive text, often written in multiple languages (including English, Latin, Italian, German, and French). Tables of contents are transcribed if included in the volume, as well as production dates and any introductory dedications by Warsher.
Pompeii (Extinct city); Archaeology -- Field work; Excavations (Archaeology) -- Pompeii (Extinct city); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Pompeii (Extinct city) -- Cartography; Italy -- History -- 20th century -- Pictorial works; Italy -- History; Art, Roman; Rome -- History, Ancient; Rostovtzeff, Michael Ivanovitch, 1870-1952; Richardson, Lawrence, Jr., 1920-2013; Duke University. Department of Classical Studies
- Regio I. Insulae 1, 5, 1954 (Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Strada Stabiana; Tombs outside the Stabian Gate; Stabian Gate; Insula 1, 1-7; Insula 1, 8: The Hospitium Hermetis; Insula 5, 1; Insula 5, 2: Tannery; Insula 5,3
- Regio I. Insula 2, 1937 (Volume 2)
  No stated table of contents.
- Regio I. Insula 3, undated (Volume 3)
  No stated table of contents. Includes introductory statement by Warscher about the Codex Topographicus.
- Regio V, 1, 26, undated (Volume 4)
  No stated table of contents. Includes introduction about Maison de Caecilius Jucundus V, I, 26.
- Regio VI. Insula 6, 1954 (Volume 5)
  No stated table of contents. Includes to the Memory of my Teacher Michail Ivanovitsch Rostovtzeff. Thanks to Dr. Lawrence Richardson.
- Regio VI. Insula 7. Volume 1, 1955 (Volume 6)
  Introduction; Insula 7, 1-2; Insula 7, 3; Insula 7, 4-6: Casa di Ercole; Insula 7, 7; Insula 7, 8; Insula 7, 9; Insula 7, 10-14; Insula 7, 15-17; Insula 7, 18: Casa di Adone Ferito. Domus M. Asellini; Insula 7, 19: Casa d'Inaco Ed Io. Domus Fabi Tyranni Et Janini.
- Regio VI. Insula 7. Volume 2, 1955 (Volume 7)
  Insula 7, 20/21: Casa Dell' Argenteria. Domus P. Antisti Maximi et Laeli Trophimi; Insula 7, 22; Insula 7, 23: Casa di Apollo. Domus A. Herennulei Communis; Insula 7, 24-25; Insula 7, 26: Public Stable; Insula 7: Exterior Views. Appendices: Curtains in Pompeian Decoration; Fercula; Stairways; Windows Over Doors, Round Windows; Jambs with Block Capitals; Waterbirds; Gardens; Miscellaneous Furniture.
- Regio VI. Insula 8. Pars 1, 1951 (Volume 8)
  No stated table of contents. Includes statement of dedicated chapter to Mr. Lawrence Richardson; Preface; Painters in Pompeii.
- Regio VI. Insula 8. Pars 2, 3, 1951 (Volume 9)
- Regio VI. Insula 8. Pars 4, 5, 1951 (Volume 10)
- Regio VI. Insula 8. Pars 6, 1951 (Volume 11)
- Regio VI. Insula 9. Part I, 1957 (Volume 12)
  Casa del Centauro.
- Regio VI. Insula 9. Part II, 1957 (Volume 13)
  Casa di Meleagro.
- Regio VI. Insula 9. Part III, 1957 (Volume 14)
- Regio VI. Insula 9, 6. Part 1, undated (Volume 15)
- Regio VI. Insula 9, 6. Part 2, undated (Volume 16)
- Regio VI. Insula 9, 6. Part 3, undated (Volume 17)
- Regio VI. Insula 9, 6. Part 4, undated (Volume 18)
- Regio VI. Insula 10, 1949 (Volume 19)
  Casa del Naviglio.
- Regio VI. Insula 10. Part 1, 1949 (Volume 20)
- Regio VI. Insula 10. Part 2, 1949 (Volume 21)
- Regio VI. Insula 10. Part 3, 1949 (Volume 22)
- Regio VI. Insula 10, 1956 (Volume 23)
  Introduction; Foreword; VI xi 1, Shop; VI xi 2, Stair to Upper Story; VI xi 3, Kitchen Garden; VI xi 18/19/20, Dwelling; VI xi 4/17, Dwelling with Officina; VI xi 5/16, Kitchen garden with Dwelling or Lupanar; VI xi 15/16, Small Dwelling (One a Lupanar?); VI xi 14, Small Dwelling; VI xi 6/13, Officina Vestiaria; VI xi (7)/11/12, Dwelling; VI xi 7, Dwelling with Garden; Vi xi 8, Dwelling Originally Connected with the Pistrinum of VI xi 9/10; VI xi 9/10, Casa del Labirinto: West Facade; South Facade; Plans and History of the Excavation; Tuscan Atrium and Adjacent Rooms (Appendix on Impluvia & Drains); Service Rooms, Pistrinium & Baths. Stairway No. 9 (Appendix on Stairways); Service Rooms; Pistrinium & Kneading Room (Appendix on Mills), (Appendix on Kneading Machines); Baths (Appendix on Mensae Agonisticae & Cylindrus); Tetrastyle Atrium and Adjacent Rooms (Appendix on Corinthian Pillar Capitals), (Appendix on Corinthian Column Capitals), (Appendix on Impluvium Arrangements); Tablinium; Peristyle (Appendix on Cistern Heads), (Appendix on Puteals), (Appendix on Potted Trees); Rooms off the South Portico of the Peristyle. Room no. 37 (Exedra). Room no. 35. Room no. 38 (Triclinium); Rooms off the North Portico of the Peristyle. Rooms nos. 39 & 40 (Triclinia), (Appendix on Mosiac). Room no. 42 (Labyrinth Exedra), (Appendix on Mosaic). Room no. 43 (Corinthian Oecus), (Appendix on Tholoi), (Appendix on Wall Paintings), (Appendix on Pavement). Room no. 46 (Cubiculum); East Facade.
- Regio VI, Insula 10, 7, undated (Volume 40)
  Casa dell'ancora nera/House of the Anchor. Domus Melissaei et Suculae.
- Regio VI. Insula 12, 1949 (Volume 24)
  Casa del Fauno. Includes statement dedicating this volume to Prof. M.I. Rostovtzeff.
- Regio VI. Insula 13, 1954 (Volume 25)
- Regio VI. Insula 14, 1-22, 1939 (Volume 26)
- Regio VI. Insula 14, 23-36, 1939 (Volume 27)
- Regio VI. Insula 14, 37-44, 1939 (Volume 28)
- Regio VII. Insula 2. Part 1, 1937/8 (Volume 29)
- Regio VII. Insula 2. Part 2, 1937/8 (Volume 30)
- Regio VII. Insula 4. Pars 1-2, 1938 (Volume 31)
- Regio VII. Insula 4. Pars 3, 1938 (Volume 32)
  Casa dei Capitelli Colorati
- Regio VII. Insula 4. Pars 4-5, 1938 (Volume 33)
  Casa del Granduca di Toscana, Casa dei Capitelli Figurati
- Regio IX, Insula 1, undated (Volume 34)
  Autographed by Tatiana Warsher.
- Regio IX, Insula 2, 1937 (Volume 35)
  Autographed by Dr. Tatiana Warsher.
- Regio IX, Insula 3. Part 1, 1955 Sept. 16 (Volume 36)
  Preface; Introduction explaining importance of Casa di Marco Lucrezio; autographed by Tatiana Warsher 16 Sept. 1955. Table of contents includes: Essay by David Block on the mystery of the five bronze figurines; IX 3 1/2: Officina infectoria; IX 3 3: Taberna; IX 3 4: Taberna; IX 3 5: Domus M. Lucreti (Casa di Marco Lucrezio, Casa delle Suonatrici); IX 3 6-13: Tabernas; IX 3 14: Taberna C. Cati Scithi; IX 3 15: Domus Philocali; IX 3 17: Taberna Q. Sallusti Inventi; IX 3 18: Taberna P. Pacci Clari; IX 3 12/20: Pistrinum-Panificium T. Genialis; IX 3 21/22: Northeast corner of the insula; IX 3 23: Dwelling; IX 3 24: Dwelling annexed to the Domus M. Lucreti, north facade; IX 3 25: Domus L. Clodi Vari; IX 3 26: Doorway blocked in antiquity.
- Regio IX, Insula 3. Part 2, undated (Volume 37)
  North ala and service rooms (Domus M. Lucreti IX 3 5); other appendices
- Regio IX, Insula 8, 6, undated (Volume 38)
  La Maison du Centennaire. Includes former owner stamp from Prof. M. Rostovtzeff, Yale.
- Appendix: Via di Mecurio, 1953 (Volume 39)